Guide to the Seventh American Forest Congress Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Seventh American Forest Congress records
1995-1996
MS 1725
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
10
(9 boxes)
The records include correspondence, statements, planning files, evaluation forms, lists, and other types of materials relating to the planning, convening, and daily work of the Seventh American Forest Congress.
American Forest Congress (7th)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John C. Gordon, 1997-1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Biographical / Historical
In January, 1995, the Yale Forest Forum, a consortium of public, business, and non-profit organizations sharing common concerns about forest conservation, organized a meeting of conservation leaders. They unanimously called for the convening of the Seventh American Forest Congress, which met in Washington, D.C. from February 20 to February 24, 1996. The congress attempted to produce a working consensus on forest conservation and recommended steps for improving forest management practices, research on forestry problems, and policies guiding both. John Gordon of the Yale University School of Forestry and Environmental Studies and Rex McCullough of Weyerhaeuser served as the congress's co-chairs.
Scope and Contents
The records include correspondence, statements, planning files, evaluation forms, lists, and other types of materials relating to the planning, convening, and daily work of the Seventh American Forest Congress.
Appendix: Video Tapes
1 Training session for roundtable facilitators at the headquarters of the Society of American Foresters, 1995 Jul 30-31 VHS T-120
2 Training session for roundtable facilitators at the headquarters of the Society of American Foresters, 1995 Jul 30-31 VHS T-120
3 Training session for roundtable facilitators at the headquarters of the Society of American Foresters, 1995 Jul 30-31 VHS T-30
4 Haddam, CT roundtable, 1995 Jul 12, 19 [rough footage] VHS T-120
5 Haddam, CT roundtable, 1995 Jul 12, 19 [four minutes of footage edited into a sixty minute continuous loop] VHS T-60
6 Savannah, GA roundtable, 1995 Sep 29 [includes presentation by Eugene Odom] VHS T-120
7 St. Paul, MN roundtable, 1995 Jun 29 VHS T-120
8 St. Paul, MN roundtable, 1995 Jun 29 VHS T-120
9 St. Paul, MN roundtable, 1995 Jun 29 VHS T-120
10 Missoula, MT roundtable, 1995 Dec 8 VHS T-120
11 Reno, NV roundtable, 1996 Jan 23 VHS 24 minutes
12 *Charlottesville, VA roundtable, 1995 Dec 15 [local television news story copyrighted by Virginia Broadcasting Company] VHS
13 Seventh American Forest Congress, Washington, DC, 1996 Feb 20-23 BCT-20G
14 Seventh American Forest Congress, Washington, DC, 1996 Feb 20-23 BCT-30G
15 Seventh American Forest Congress, Washington, DC, 1996 Feb 20-23 BCT-30G
16 Seventh American Forest Congress, Washington, DC, 1996 Feb 20-23 BCT-20G
17 Seventh American Forest Congress, Washington, DC, 1996 Feb 20-23 BCT-20G
18 Seventh American Forest Congress, Washington, DC, 1996 Feb 20-23 BCT-20G
19 Seventh American Forest Congress, Washington, DC, 1996 Feb 20-23 BCT-20G
20 Seventh American Forest Congress, Washington, DC, 1996 Feb 20-23 BCT-30G
Forest conservation; Forest management; Forests and forestry -- United States -- Congresses; Gordon, J. C. (John C.), 1939-; American Forest Congress (7th) -- Washington, D.C. -- 1996
- Original accession, Accession 1997-M-147
  - Administrative
    - Summary/overview handout (Box 1)
  - Congress background
    - American Forest Congress history (Box 1)
    - Yale Forest Forum
      - Meetings, prior to 1995 January 1 (Box 1)
      - Nebraska Roundtable, 1995 January 1 (Box 1)
  - Congress planning
    - Senior Sponsors Board
      - Ambassadors-at-large (Box 1)
    - Board of directors
      - Meetings
        - 1995
          - Feb 9-10 (Box 1)
          - Mar 23 (Box 1)
          - Apr 13 (Box 1)
          - May 25 (Box 1)
          - Jun 22 (Box 1)
          - Sep 20-21 (Box 1)
          - Dec 2-3 (Box 1)
        - 1996 Apr 18-19 (Box 1)
      - Transition team (Box 1)
  - Congress implementation
    - Committees--General (Box 1)
    - National Program Committee
      - Congress process development (Box 1)
      - Leadership program (Box 1)
      - Diversity (Box 1)
      - Concurrent discussion sessions (Box 1)
      - Support team (Box 1)
    - Local Arrangements Committee
      - Sheraton Washington Hotel (Box 1)
      - Arrangement Committee handbook (Box 1)
      - Exhibition Services (GES) (Box 1)
      - Marketing plan (Box 1)
      - Registration materials (Box 1)
      - Cancellation insurance (Box 1)
      - Signs (Box 1)
      - Supplies (Box 1)
      - Audio-visual (Box 1)
      - Participant packet information (Box 1)
    - Citizens' Involvement Committee
      - Citizens' response form (Box 2)
    - Communications Committee
      - References (Box 2)
      - Draft communications material (Box 2)
      - Final communications material (Box 2)
    - Education Committee (Box 2)
    - Management Committee (Box 2)
    - Policy Committee (Box 2)
    - Research Committee (Box 2)
    - Forest Constituency Committee
      - Scholarships (Box 2)
  - Local Roundtables
    - Roundtables by region (Box 2)
    - Roundtable videos
      - Roundtables for the Seventh American Forest Congress [Art Smyth shortened video] (Box 2)
      - Orientation for local Roundtables [includes video] (Box 2)
    - Publicity for Roundtables (Box 2)
  - Citizen input
    - Mail, phone, FAX (Box 2)
  - Cooperating organizations (Box 2)
  - Original material completed by participants
    - Table commitment cards, 1996 February 21 (Box 3)
    - Vision elements [principles of future care for forests], 1996 February 21 (Box 3)
    - Vision enhancements, 1996 February 21 (Box 3)
    - Vision elements/additional elements of vision, 1996 February 22 (Box 3)
    - Vision elements, 1996 February 23 (Box 3)
    - New principles affirmation sheet, 1996 February 23 (Box 3)
    - Vision work, 1996 February 21 (Box 4)
    - Back home, next steps (Box 4)
    - Advice to Board of Directors (Box 4)
    - Vision revisions, team notes, 1996 February 22 (Box 4)
    - Individual commitments, 1996 February 24 (Box 4)
    - Principle statement worksheets, 1996 February 22 (Box 4)
    - Daily evaluation forms, 1996 February 21 (Box 4)
    - Daily evaluation forms, 1996 February 22 (Box 5)
    - Congress feedback forms (Box 5)
    - Laurie Wayburn's principle themes and workshop groupings, 1996 February 23
      - Multiple votes on single sheet [results of votes on various principles] (Box 5)
      - Other groupings [of principles] (Box 5)
      - Policy grouping (Box 5)
      - Global (Box 5)
      - Incentives/economics (Box 5)
      - Management and stewardship (Box 5)
      - Ethics/values (Box 5)
      - Sustainability (Box 5)
      - Property rights and responsibilities (Box 5)
      - Research and education (Box 5)
      - Education and communication (Box 5)
      - Communities (Box 5)
      - Decision-making process (Box 5)
      - Research and science (Box 5)
      - Conflict resolution (Box 5)
      - Biodiversity (Box 5)
  - People/organizations receiving information about the congress (Box 6)
  - Project chronological correspondence file
    - #1, 1995 May-August (Box 6)
    - #2, 1995 August-September (Box 7)
    - #3, 1995 August-October (Box 7)
    - #4, 1995 November- 1996 January (Box 7)
    - #5, 1996 January-March (Box 7)
- Additional material, 1995-1996; Accession 1998-M-116
  Scope and Contents
  This accession includes twenty video tapes from the Seventh American Forest Congress and local roundtables that preceded it. Original video tapes may not be viewed. For information on copies created for research use, consult the Video Tapes appendix
  - Map of local roundtables leading up to the congress (Box 8)
  - Poster summarizing the results of the Minnesota roundtable, 1995 June (Box 8)
    General note
    See: CF90
  - Video tapes
    - Training session for roundtable facilitators, 1995 Jul 30-31 [tapes 1-3] (Box 1)
    - Local roundtables
      - Connecticut [tapes 4-5], 1995 July (Box 1)
      - Georgia [tape 6], 1995 September (Box 1)
      - Minnesota [tapes 7-9], 1995 June (Box 1)
      - Montana [tape 10], 1995 December (Box 1)
      - Nevada [tape 11], 1996 January (Box 1)
      - Virginia [tape 12], 1995 December (Box 2)
      - Seventh American Forest Congress [tapes 13-20], 1996 February 20-24 (Box 2)